All right. And I'm just admitting
everybody now. We'll just take
a minute here. All right. I think
everybody who was waiting in the lobby
is admitted now. So, we should be good
to start.
>> Good morning, everyone. My name is Horge
Gonzalez. I'm the medical psilocybin
program manager. Thank you uh for being
here this morning. Uh we have our chair
Ian Dunn uh who will be facilitating
today's meeting. But as a reminder, I
want you to know that this meeting is
being recorded. Please remember to keep
language appropriate as the recordings
are made public on the advisory board
website. Um so with that, uh Ian, please
take it away.
>> All righty. Good morning everyone and
happy Monday. Uh this is the meeting of
the dosage administration and clinical
practice committee. Um, I just wanted to
say welcome. Thank you all for being
here. I know it is a Monday, so we all
wish we could have slept in a little bit
more, but we will persevere. Um,
so today we're going to be going over
preparation, integration, and and
administration sessions. Um the last
document we worked through, I took a lot
of the notes from there and um just kind
of clarified where the facilitators and
the um like recommener or certifier is.
Um but as a quick reminder to anyone who
is um new to committees, they operate in
an advisory capacity and they provide
forum for individuals who may be experts
but may not serve on the board due to
real or perceived conflicts of interest.
They support the board by expanding
community input, incorporating subject
matter expertise, and increasing
participation in program development. I
will now turn over to the department to
unmute. If you want to share your name,
role of or area of expertise and your
perspective or interest related to um
dosage administration, clinical
practice, um I will give an opportunity
for that now.
>> All right. Um, so yeah, if you'd like to
introduce yourself, um, there is an icon
at the top uh that says raise uh with a
hand above it. Um, and uh you can go
ahead and click that and then I will
enable your mic. Um, so first uh looks
like we've got Chris Biscus. Uh, Chris,
your mic's enabled. You can unmute when
ready.
>> Good morning everybody. Chris Pasky
here. I'm a board member and I'm a
facilitator in Colorado.
>> Awesome. Thanks, Chris. And next we've
got Denali Wilson. Denali, your mic is
enabled.
>> Morning everyone. Morning, Chair Dunn.
Um, grateful to be here. My name is
Denali Wilson. I am the director of
strategic support for the healing
advocacy fund, which is a nonprofit that
supports state regulated access. Um, and
yeah, that's it.
All right, thanks Denelli. And next
we've got uh James Brown. Uh James, your
mic is enabled.
>> Morning everyone and thank you again
Ian. How you doing? Um my name is James
Brown. I'm a doctor of pharmacy here in
New Mexico. I'm a practicing pharmacist.
I'm a facilitator trained. I'm
representing an organization called Five
Degrees North Healing Foundation. It's
nonprofit and I'm just happy to be here
to share today. Thank you so much.
Awesome.
Thanks, James. Um, oh, and Chris, um,
did you raise your hand again or is that
just left over?
>> That's just left over. Sorry.
>> Okay. Yeah, you're good. Um, and also,
yeah, if anyone would like to introduce
themselves in the chat as well, you can.
Uh, you're more than welcome to do that
as well.
>> Perfect. All righty. And then would you
bring up the document?
>> I sure will.
Here you go, Ian.
>> All righty. So, this is a new um
preparation document taking into
consideration what we talked about at
the last meeting. Um, it seemed there
was a little bit of confusion between
where the certifier or recommener lied
and where the facilitator did. I hope
that this one works to clear that up a
little bit. Um, so let's just get
started and go through it. So
preparation participants shall be
referred by a provider with prescriptive
authority who determines clinical
appropriateness and assigns a clinical
support tier based on evaluation of
medical history, mental health history,
medication interactions, and current
psychological functioning. Participants
shall complete at at least two
preparation sessions totaling no less
than 3 hours prior to administration
with each session lasting at least 1
hour and occurring no less than 24 hours
and no more than 60 days before
administration. Preparation shall be
conducted by the facilitator present
during um
during administration whenever feasible
may occur via teleaalth record
tellahalth when clinically appropriate
and shall be documented in the
participant record. Uh informed consent
shall be obtained through direct
discussion and shall not be satisfied
solely by written acknowledgement. The
discussion shall include risks,
benefits, uncertainty, psychological and
physical effects, altered states of
consciousness, potential impairment of
decision-making, and disclosure that
psilocybin has not been approved by the
FDA. Written disclosure shall include
facilitator identity, permit number,
qualifications, any ceremonial
components, and the right of both the
participant and facilitator to terminate
services.
Preparation shall include orientation to
the treatment process including the role
and scope of the facilitator and
expected expectations before during and
after administration and shall include
development of an integration plan.
Participants shall discuss goals,
intentions and expectations and
preparation shall address set and
setting factors including psychological
readiness, environmental conditions,
privacy, accommodations and safety.
A safety and support plan shall be
developed and shall include emergency
procedures, facility safety protocols,
access to emergency medical services,
and post session transportation
arrangements.
Participants shall not operate a motor
vehicle for at least 24 hours following
administration. Preparation shall also
establish clear boundaries, including
participant preferences regarding
physical touch, consent processes, and
disclosure of any additional persons or
recording during the session. For group
administration, at least one individual
session shall be required. Participants
shall be informed of group size,
facilitator to participant ratio,
interaction expectations,
confidentiality, and physical contacts
and considerations.
And then all preparation activities
shall be documented in the participant
record, including session details,
informed consent, clinical screening
rule results, clinical support to your
placement, safety planning, and
confirmation of eligibility. Preparation
shall occur sufficiently proximate to
administration to remain clinically
relevant and shall not be conducted in a
rushed or p purely procedural manner.
All right, I will open for um comments,
questions, concerns um or necessary
additions for the preparation session.
>> All right, and we've got hands up. Uh
Denali, I see your hand first and you
can unmute when ready.
Hi. Um, I yeah, these are just first
thoughts and would um am eager to hear
what other people think. A couple of
things that jump out. I'm a little
nervous about prescribing what we
include in the patient record just
because of um provider liability, right?
We want providers who are billing to be
able to um
put what is necessary for billing but
not um you know raise any flags. Um so
if for preparation right that should be
build and documented as a psychotherapy
interaction rather than something
specific to the program I think that's
probably going to be necessary to
protect our providers. Um, and then I
just had,
so it says here, um,
two preparation sessions including
totally no less than 3 hours. I don't
I'm not a provider, so I don't know what
that looks like from billing amounts,
but I I don't know if you're able to do
two um that are 3 hours. I don't know
what the billing um like time
differentials are, but I think an hour
might be the max. So, if that's what we
want, then it would be three. um but
would would like other provider
expertise on on those two pieces of
feedback.
>> Yeah, and I do appreciate your comment.
The one thing I will like clarify is a
lot of the information that is stored in
the participant record is mostly for the
state program management. So, it's not
going to be the direct like EHR that
they're going to use for um like billing
and administrative processes that
already occur in their practice. This is
just all we have to store for the
program so that when we are um
looking at
if they were doing anything wrong it's
handled within um the state and not
within the insurance billing codes if
that makes sense.
>> All right. Um let's see. And next we've
got Eene Brewer. Um and Eileen if uh
before you un or sorry um before your
comment as well if you could just
introduce yourself.
>> Absolutely. Thanks. Um my name is Eileen
Brewer. I am a expert in uh pain and
psychedelics. Um and I'm an advocate for
that. Um on the preparation I was uh
thinking that three hours preparation is
a lot. Um and I can see requiring that
the first time but many people need
additional sessions and I think it
should be clarified that maybe 3 hours
shouldn't be required every single time
they they are going to have an
administration session. The first time I
can see but after that it may not be
necessary to have that much preparation.
Um in addition to that my other thought
was uh for group administration on um
the requirements are that the person has
to have at least one individual
preparation session but I think it might
also be beneficial if there is a
requirement that the group whoever they
are has to meet prior to the
administration session as well. That way
you can sort out any of those um
personality conflicts that might arise.
You don't want to be doing that during
an administration session. I don't think
those are my thoughts. Thanks so much.
Awesome. Thank you. Um let's see. And
next we've got Ann Mets. Um and I have
enabled your mic. You can unmute when
ready.
>> Yes. Um my comment is regarding the
requirement that um the participant have
to be referred by a provider with
prescriptive authority. Um I really
think that anybody who has within the
scope of practice the ability to treat
and diagnose psychiatric and mental
health conditions really ought to be
able to make these referrals. I sort of
feel like having to go through um a
primary care provider to access
treatment is a little bit uh limiting
and that really licensed mental health
professionals in the state ought to be
able to make these referrals.
So that's all I had to say.
>> Yeah, thank you. Um
I Okay, so New Mexico is a very
interesting state in that we are one of
the few states to allow um sides and
PhDs to prescribe if they um complete a
psycho pharmarmacology course that would
grant them a prescriptive authority to
um prescribe even if they are not a
physician or nurse practitioner or
physician's assistant or one of the
million other titles that can prescribe.
Um
>> well, one of the one of the issues is
the majority of the providers in our
state are actually M's level and thus
they're not able to participate in the
prescriptive authority and I have a PhD
but mine is a research and teaching PhD.
Um so I wouldn't have prescriptive
authorities. I think if you look at like
the workforce population for the state
of New Mexico, you know, there are very
few sides and psychologists. And so I
really think it's important for M's
level social workers, counselors,
marriage and family therapists to be
able to make this referral.
So if you have an ability to diagnose, I
think you ought to be able to have the
ability to refer.
Sounds I will definitely consider that.
Um, I'm going to pend on what the law
defines um
the person who can provide while I get
that information. I will definitely let
another person speak. But um if that is
lawful, then we could move forward with
that. But I do want to hear what other
people want to say as well.
>> All right. Next, uh we've got Chris
Pisces. Chris, you can unmute when
ready.
>> Using a saw. I'm going to go to the next
person. Can you come back to me, please?
>> All right, sounds good. Um, let's see.
So, next we've got uh James Brown. And
James, you can unmute when you're ready.
Ian, my thought on this um great start.
Thank you so much for doing this, by the
way. Um the group was my thought too.
First thought was on the group was we
need to maybe add at least one group
session. I do think that that's very
important that was brought up earlier
and that was my thought too is that when
we do groups we'd like them to meet at
least once. It's just very important for
the bonding and intentions to be set.
There's a lot of stuff that we set in
that group setting that are just it
could be brief even you know but I think
that's important. Also prescriptive
authority was on my thought too is is
when we talk about prescriptive
authority um I definitely want to have
more discussion around that thought is
besides our normal PAs, nurse
practitioners, MD, psychologist um even
for us in our realm we can prescribe
certain things um under the clinician
act. Um and so I think that you know
access is important here to think about
when we think about these things with
access to is New Mexico is very rural,
very limited and I think this is going
to limit us. I think I really think that
this is could be a stopper um as far as
access to certain people around the
state. Just a thought. Um I'd like to
see a little bit of expanded on who can
refer. Thoughts? That's all. Thank you.
>> Thank you.
>> All right. And Larry, it looks like
you're last hand up for now.
>> Yeah. Good. Thanks. Larry Leman, I'm
also on the advisory board and chair of
the end of life committee. Um I I have a
few different comments. Um, one is I I I
I strongly agree that the group needs to
meet and I don't think that should be a
brief meeting. I think the group work is
actually relatively complex and um I
would suggest that the group needs to
have like a whatever we can decide in
the time frame but I think that that
dynamic is really um important. The
other is that I think that these are
good overall guidelines, but I think
that each of the four conditions may
need to have some way to be being more
specific and to to vary from this. And
let me give a couple of examples. Um,
we've talked about the end of life where
um the end of life committee is hoping
that be happening for some people in
their homes that it may be appropriate
for the facilitator to be there
initially but maybe not for the whole
session. potentially there could be a a
death dueler or somebody who is
delegated. So I think that may be a
different situation for each thing and
similarly um
when we're talking about like PTSD um I
I think it may not be enough prep. I
mean if you're working with people that
have like complex PTSD um and then they
may need to have a longer individual and
groupoup session. So I I I would
encourage us to have some writing in
there that that indicates that that
there may be a difference for for
different um you know different
conditions there. I also would agree
with the person who did mention about
the prep doesn't need to be as long for
the second time. That reflects what we
do in the clinical trials. Like for the
clinical trials of depression, we have a
a minimum of six hours for the first
prep but at 90 minutes for the for the
second one. So, I think that's good
advice to be able to shorten the uh the
prep.
Thank you very much.
>> Thank you.
>> All right. And we will go back to Chris.
Um see he's got his hand up again.
>> Yeah. Sorry everybody. I'm trying to
find a quiet place here. But um so first
I'm curious, we had a document we were
working off of last week and that
are we just dropping that and going to
this now? Um
>> so the document last week that we were
working on was having a lot of confusion
between the referer and the like
facilitator who's actually going to be
doing the preparation session. And so
because of that, this one was cleaned up
and then also took the notes from that
other one. Uh like in the last meeting
we talked about um that's where we came
up with the the 3 hours two sessions was
at the last meeting. Um but
still subject to change like nothing was
firmly adopted. Um but in order to
provide more clarity uh that's where
this document came from.
>> Okay. Um, so I
I think this is fairly short for
um
defining what preparation requirements
are going to be required for this. And
um I do agree with Ann about
adopting a more broad
um
language rather than prescriber for who
can refer to this program. I think that
was kind of been the intent
this uh entire you know prep up to this
point was that we're going to have you
know broad definitions of what a
clinician is and who can provide these
services. Um and I also
agree with um
Dr. Leman that, you know, we should have
um maybe
I don't know if a tiered system would
work best or um
some way to,
you know, find an appropriate amount of
prep work. and and I on top of that I
think that three hours might even be too
much for some people. U so I'm not sure
what the best way to approach that is
you know I think a lot of it needs to be
left up to the clinician to
u kind of make that determination with
people based on their circumstances.
But yeah, those are some initial
thoughts I have.
Well, thank you. So, I definitely agree
with the group part. So, um I posted in
the chat kind of got a little bit lost,
but um basically for group
administration, I can say at least one
individual preparation or session shall
be required. At least one hour of group
preparation shall occur in the group
setting. This may be counted as part of
the total preparation hours. Um,
participants shall be informed of group
size, facilitator to participant ratio,
interaction expectations,
confidentiality, and physical contact
considerations.
Is that a better um group one or did we
want to change that as well?
I saw a a thumbs up. Um, James Brown put
in the chat for the language
preparation,
uh, two sections, initial participation
and requirements and subsequent
participation and requirements.
Okay. And I also see Robert has his hand
up. Um, Rob, if you like to unmute.
just to clarify.
>> Oh, I think um is your boom up?
>> Uh as usual, as usual, my boom is up in
the sky. I am Robert Truckner. I'm the
medical director. Ian, I just wanted to
add that the definition in the law for
clinician means an approved health care
provider licensed in New Mexico who
holds a permit from the department to
provide medical services to qualified
patients. No strict mention of
prescriptive power in that. Thanks.
>> Thank you. I did want to reference that
the definition though for qualified
patient means a patient whose clinician
has judged the patient to be medically
appropriate candidate for the use of
medical psilocybin based on being
diagnosed with a qualifying condition.
And I don't know any other profession
other than those with prescriptive
authority that have the ability to weigh
the medical use of anything other than
prescriptive authority. So, is there
another area where
like an
like a licensed clinical counselor or
social worker are recommending
a specific medical product?
Ian, I'm not sure that the group is
having a lot of discussions about this
internally at at this point in time. Um,
so I'm I I am enjoying hearing all your
opinions as we kind of go forward to
think about this in general. And I don't
think I'm speaking ahead of myself.
We're not necessarily, well, we haven't
decided, but I'm not sure that we're
necessarily looking at prescriptive
power as a necessity to recommend this
treatment because really there's no
prescription
uh of an illegal drug. So, it it may
fall back more to the cannabis rules
that that suggest the referring provider
can certify or recommend
um the treatment,
>> right? And I'm not saying that we're
going to write a prescription for
psilocybin, but I believe also in
medical cannabis, it is a um
it is limited to those with prescriptive
authority, is it not?
>> That is correct.
>> All right. Thank you. and Denali.
>> Yeah. Um, great discussion.
I am reflecting on this moment of the
discussion on a couple in a couple of
ways. One, right, this is um, and I know
we all know this, right? Not cannabis
where we're thinking about the
intervention pharmacologically, right?
And I think that that's helpful for
understanding who is making the
referral. I think the closer analogy
because the the program is about a
therapeutic intervention, right? We've
had many discussions across
subcommittees and in the um full
advisory board about the therapeutic
container being the critical piece that
um you know delivers care and that just
is so dramatically different from
cannabis. And so I would think of it and
you said um you said you know thinking
about uh recommending a medical product.
We're recommending here a a clinical
intervention. So in the same way that
non-prescriber
therapists can recommend EMDR or other
interventions based on um an appropriate
diagnosis. I think that that maybe is
the paradigm shift that's helpful for
understanding.
I guess my concern for it is in the
patient qualification and safety
committee and in how they're working
with the clinical support tiers, they
have to be able to understand what the
medications are doing because if I say
allow a social worker to recommend
psilocybin but they don't know the
pharmarmacology of the medications that
they are on, they can't establish lish a
baseline of is this going to be safe? Do
we need to authorize an an outside
dosage? Do we need to um take other
steps to ensure that the medication
works? For instance, SSRIs tend to
really blunt um psychedelic effects. So,
do we need to give them a higher dose?
Um what if they're on a GLP1 and all of
the sudden they think it's not working.
we give them a higher dose and then 3
days later um it all hits them at the
same time because they have lower GI
motility. So those are my kind of bigger
concerns is who's then going to do the
analysis of their health history of what
um is going on because I don't think we
have the resources to train every single
recommener on this. that would just be
sending them to
graduate school in a medical field. Um
because there are so many different
evaluations.
Most
clinical remedies don't require taking a
substance. And that's where this the
differentiation becomes apparent because
now we have to evaluate medication
interactions. Now we have to evaluate
other things. And while even the best
provider may not be, you know, 10 of 10
on an on
analyzing those things, I think it is
safer to have someone who was trained on
that to be the one to say, "Okay, now
let's go ahead and make sure you can get
this because I've at least ensured that
you are going to be safe in the
program."
Um,
Lisa,
>> right? And I have enabled your mic. you
can unmute.
>> Thank you. Um I agree with what Denali
just shared. Uh I think she has a really
good point and uh to your point and um I
don't think if prescriber is unless
prescriber is also a facilitator they
might not be trained on the pharmacology
of psilocybin and other drug
interactions. uh and uh that can be a
concern and to my understanding it's
facilitator's job to
do
the diligence and preparation and
establish the right dose and understand
which medications the client is on
before going in a session with them.
And I I
back to Denal's point, cannabis was
meant to be consumed at home or outside
of um outside of the dispensary where
psilocybin will be consumed under the
supervision of licensed facilitators.
Therefore, I think there's no real need
for only prescribers to be able to admin
uh to prescribe so heaven.
>> Thank you. Yeah, but even in a hospital
setting,
you still have to get a prescription.
Like the nurses, even though you're
under constant clinical supervision,
can't just say, "Oh, you're anxious.
Here's some Adavan." Like, there's
always a person that is reviewing the
entire chart. And in a hospital, that's
there's a pharmacist to review their um
their all of their medications together.
There's a doctor to review their current
situation and what they need. And then
there's the nurses who are doing their
assessments to making sure that they're
working in the right direction. And even
under all of those circumstances, we
still have a prescription. So is there
an instance where we're not getting a
prescription to administer
a drug or anything where they are
physically taking something?
Uh Chris
Um,
so I guess I
want to kind of point us towards the
Colorado model. You know, up there they
use kind of a
for black lack of a better word, a
flowchart where if you know, patients
have
um these concerning
aspects to their treatment plan that
they need higher consultation. And you
know maybe that's something we can bring
in here where if there's a heavy risk of
drug interaction we you know it requires
consultation with a um a prescribing
authority but ultimately psilocybin has
an incredibly high safety profile. So it
seems
this seems to be very
troubling that we're heading this
direction with prescriptive authority
for people that can refer. Um and
ultimately we're putting a lot of the
power in the hands that I in my opinion
to people that really don't have the
knowledge to carry this. Um this is a
little bit different of a um a product
than our traditional medical system has
encountered in the past.
>> All right. And James
>> Ian and everyone thoughts on this one
really is the referral is who can refer.
If we really step back and think about
the referer, maybe we open we should
open that up to more people who can
refer. That's not the person necessarily
determining the clinical
appropriateness. Does that make sense?
Ian, like are we saying that the
clinical appropriateness and the taring
that we've been doing comes from the
referral and the referring psychologist
or MD? Or is that somebody separate? Is
that the person that's psychedelically
trained that would then say you're tier
based off of this now here's your and we
don't want to say prescription, right?
We want to use the words here's your
dose, right? Or here's your therapy,
right? And so are we saying so break
that back down again. So are we saying
the referral anybody can refer or are we
saying that the deterinee
right is the one who determines
that is that need to be the same person
I don't necessarily think so um I think
the deterine needs to be trained like
we've talked about and needs to
understand the tears and understand the
patient I think we need to open up the
referers but the deterine needs to be
trained and specific and I think maybe
that's the prescription is under the
termine and so That's just my thought.
Thank you.
>> Yeah. And I mean that is relevant. I
mean so in what I was picturing is the
clinical support tier the all of the the
medical side of the model would happen
very much at the beginning. That's when
you would have your your interaction
with the all the things that make New
Mexico's law unique. And then once you
get to the facilitator, that's where you
get to your social workers, your
clinical counselors, um people who are
going to be there. And then they could
be facilitators or they could be
integrators and or both, some
combination, and just kind of helping
them out. But in terms of evaluating
medical readiness that I had put on the
refer to say, hey, you need a clinical
support tier. I'm going to look at your
past history, whether you have um a
disqualifying condition, whether you are
taking a medication that is going to
increase seizure threshold or whatever.
Um and make sure that you're not, you
know, acutely intoxicated and are
psychologically ready for psilocybin
administration.
If we're going to take out with
prescriptive authority, then what is the
who is eligible to refer
I guess would be my question.
All right. And see Lisa Ginsburg's hand
up again. And Lisa, I've enabled your
mic.
Thank you. And I think my uh concern I
just want to reemphasize it again. Um
it's all about the training. If the
person who will be referring is not the
same person who will be facilitating
that implies that the referer needs to
be properly trained on a dozing on the
counter medication and all these
disqualifications
which
raises additional question how you going
to reach to these people's uh fear to
make them aware of what the
disqualifications are if they not let's
say suicide facilitators or planning to
be
>> right so the referers would still go
through training um like even for the
medical cannabis program they'd complete
um a department training to be able to
refer people so it would be a similar
thing to that it would be an additional
um pharmacological
class on psilocybin its effects because
once you know a lot about uh different
receptor typ and binding. A lot of um
problems you can much more easily
predict. Of course, it's better to use
what the evidence is saying and not
predict it based on a theoretical
perspective, but a lot of them you can
you can start to to envision it. Um, so
I I would still imagine that the referer
would be trained just how they are for
the medical cannabis program and then um
it would then refer to
um someone who is trained on actually
dealing with the medication, actually
helping the patients through their
experience because that would be a whole
different training, right? uh to in
order to facilitate that's very
different from just you know kind of
analysis of benefits and and
cons. Um, Denali.
>> Um, okay. Okay. So to the question of
like who makes the
right like where the clinical expertise
comes in I think this is where we're
circling around and I I'm grateful again
and I know we've talked about it um
already today but looking back at the
statute right we've defined the
conditions for or we've defined what the
inquiry is right yes there is this piece
about determining whether the um
intervention is medically appropriate
for a candidate. But we also said that
that determination like we defined how
to make that determination and it is
based only on the diagnosis of a
qualifying condition. And I think that
the concern for needing additional
clinical attention is really appropriate
especially where there are maybe
contraindications or there might be
other medication. And I think um maybe
Chris has more expertise on on this in
the the the Colorado model, but there's
as I understand it like a two track,
right? So um if you know if XYZ then you
know you have to engage with a more
clinical um facilitator and and
something like that may be appropriate.
You know I think Dr. Leman had to jump
off, but we were talking about complex
PTSD as maybe being somewhere where our
care model and the people who are
involved look different, right? Our our
our training requirements um and uh you
know the the qualifications of people
who are engaged. We're maybe going to
have a more diverse multiddisciplinary
team based on the acuity of what someone
is experiencing. Um, so I think that
what I'm hearing from the group is maybe
not a rejection of this heightened
clinical standard, but that we make it
appropriate to the circumstances where
it's needed and not just across the
board.
>> Yeah. And I don't necessarily disagree
with the sentiment that it can't be it
has to be someone with prescriptive
authority. My concern is that where who
is going to do this like assessment and
that's kind of where it's it bothers me
a little bit because unlike Colorado or
Oregon, we are the only state that
actually has a referral process. We need
someone to refer and
given the how our medical system works
as of now, the role most fitting is a
prescriber just on the grounds that they
already are analyzing
um what is medically appropriate and
what if the benefits outweigh um the
cons. And so I just that's where I'm
coming from. It's not from like I think
that prescriptive people with
prescriptive authority never make any
mistakes. No, no, no, no. Trust me, I've
seen more than my fair share. But um
it's saying that like we our program
inherently
by the legislation is different from
those two states. And in honoring the
legislative intent, it would be to um
have some kind of referral. But I will
again defer back uh James
Ian and group you know back to that I
we're right on topic here. I think this
is very important. um some of the
terminology
um the participant shall be right and
and I think that we go back to the New
Mexico Healthcare Act and you know
because if a person can be somebody that
is a facilitator in this program and we
are different than Colorado and we are
different than Oregon because this is a
medical model and so if we say that an
RN let's say Ian right or another a PTO
or dentist or somebody else that's can
be a facilitator
And some of those people are also
prescribers.
Um, you know, how can they also refer?
You know, how how can these people who
are family therapists who are
counselors, how do they refer? And then
how also do people in the the community
of the death doulas or the community of
the clergy, how do they refer? You know,
we don't want to cut the the clergy out
or those death doulas who are actively
in those disease states and and refer.
So I think if we go maybe we can use a
different terminology as far as shall be
um just thoughts you know just looking
at that uh maybe it's you know we just
can be the participants
there's multiple ways to refer and then
I'm with you on the determinant once the
determinant is done so in our model what
we're trying to look at is when we have
our center we get referrals that's what
we're hoping on right we'd get people to
refer to us and then we have the MDs we
have the therapists I have the people
that are prescriptive authority right
now and then I would have them do the
intake
right so they would do the intake and
then do the determination on the
clinical appropriateness so I think
that's where we kind of split this up
and we say referrals can be done by all
these people and but we say the
termination and a clinical
appropriateness is done by the
prescriptive authority person and then
that allows that tier-based and and
appropriateness to be set just a thought
again you know just another section we
break it up into couple sections for
referral section and open that up and
then we just say determination and
clinical appropriateness is determined
by the p the person doing this tier work
and that's through the intake. Thank
you.
>> I actually really like that that model
um where yeah I could I could definitely
get behind what you were saying there.
Um
yeah, I just really I really liked it.
No further comment. Uh and
Um I think I think um one thing that's
sort of important to keep in mind is
that at this point psilocybin is not a
treatment for anything and you know the
other states that have adopted
state-based programs have thread this
needle by basically saying this is
nondirective treatment and so I think
the idea that this needs a prescription
um presupposes that there's a treatment
that's approved
um for it and so I think that in the
situation that we're in where it's not
actually an approved treatment. Um, it's
a little bit more nuanced,
you know, and we have to sort of, I
think, adopt a little bit of what the
other states have done, which is to sort
of say this is a non-directive nword,
um, you know, treatment, but it's not a
treatment for X. Um, you know, and I
think the other thing too is that, um,
you know, I mean, I recognize Ian that
you put these, you know, these documents
together, but I really, you know, I
think a prepoundonderance of the voices
that we're hearing are really saying we
need to broaden this. And so I do hope
that we put this question up to a vote.
>> Yeah. Um so what we're going this is all
just discussion drafts. So I'm actually
working on the um language for James's
recommendation.
But
what
is different is a this document never
says the word prescription. It says a
provider with prescriptive authority.
meaning they could write a prescription.
They're not going to they're just going
to refer a patient. But um actually what
James was saying was that they may be
referred by any clinician. Um
but
>> well I think that's where screening is
really helpful and when facilitators are
trained in the tier model and then they
can say like okay this person's been
referred to me they have treatment
resistant depression they have no other
medical complications. Do we really need
to bring in a third-party
medical provider in a state that has
like really difficult has a lot of
difficulty with access? I'm just sort of
saying that we're creating all of these
barriers that I don't think really need
to be there,
>> right? But if we're we can't do the
system where there's just no one's going
to check, right? I don't think that's
safe for anyone. If we just say, "Oh,
well, they just had treatment resistant
depression. I'm not going to follow up
at all and then we're just going to send
them on their way." I don't think that's
beneficial. I think it we need someone
to say, "Okay, I'm going to assess. I'm
going to say, okay, you know what? Just
like they do for medical cannabis, I'm
going to certify a recommendation saying
that the benefits outweigh the costs."
And once that certification is done,
that's when the facilitator gets kind of
on board, they're the ones that are
going to have um a dosage range to kind
of select from. They are going to if
they need to split a dose, if they need
um whatever you know their process is,
I'm not going to tell them how to do
their um job while we're not creating
the facilitator requirements here. Um,
so
>> well I mean I would say that I would say
that again like the qualification is a
diagnosis and so if you are able to make
a diagnosis in the state of New Mexico
that's really what that's really what it
should kind of boil come down to. It's
like if you can make the diagnosis.
>> I have to ask what other substance do we
give people just based on diagnosis and
not assessment?
>> Well, assessment comes prior to
diagnosis,
>> right? but of clinical readiness of that
it's going to be like for instance you
can diagnose that they have high blood
pressure and give them a beta blocker
but if their heart rate is at 70 that
might not be the best idea
like there's different angles to it a
diagnosis doesn't automatically make a a
treatment correct and I think that's
where we're having this this stumbling
is because
where are we going to say Okay. Where
are we going to have someone with
medical background say you are safe to
take this?
>> I mean the thing we're missing.
>> I mean Colorado and Oregon for instance
has had 18,000 sessions and they've had
less than 20 adverse events. I mean, I
do think that like if you've completed a
psilocybin facilitator training in the
state of New Mexico, that qualifies you
to be able to make some of these
determinations. Obviously, it's good to
be in, you know, in conversation with
other medical providers, particularly if
there are um co-occurring conditions.
But I think um you know, I think that's
what we're training people to do. And
I'll yield back the rest of my time
because I feel like this is getting to
not be useful.
Yeah, no worries. Um,
again, my thing is just safety. I know
that there aren't a huge number of
adverse effects, but as soon as there
are one, they will as soon as there are
a good number, especially with a new
program, they're going to cut the
funding for it. So, I don't want to take
the risk of creating an unsafe program
where we aren't going to have them
reviewed by someone who has
medical expertise.
We're then going to have them just go
straight to the dosage. To me, that
sounds unsafe. We can have a vote on it.
Um,
but to me, that does sound unsafe. Chris
Okay. So our medical professionals are
not trained in silicon as it is right
now. So they actually have to take
training as well to all of a sudden
become the experts on whether this
we can safely administer this to
somebody. And this is different again
than other medical procedures. We have
to be more flexible and adopt as broad
as we can of a definition of who can
refer for this medicine. Um
yeah, I think I'll get to agree with Ann
overwhelmingly everybody's telling you
like we need to open this up as broadly
as we can
>> and so
>> okay
>> um
>> so I will strike it and say pairant may
be referred by any clinician
>> uh Lisa
>> thank you and I agree with Chris and
people that uh spoke earlier. Um I think
if you would enforce additional training
on the prescribers uh then that needs to
be communicated with the board of
education because currently there's only
conversation around creating training
and potentially cutting corners and
hours in that training to make sure that
they are licensed facilitators by the
end of the year. So that that's already
a concern. But now we're talking about
creating additional modules specifically
for prescribers. That needs to be
definitely communicated as soon as
possible to the board of education. So
training programs like Chunga Institute
can start preparing and laying the
ground for that. Um I think being able
to determine whether someone is on GLP1
or other substances does not really
eliminate
adverse reactions. and risk reaction
most likely and often happen due to
psychological reasons. Um, which would
be outside of scope of training for the
prescriber.
Um, and I I think that creates
additional hoops where we have to send a
person to a prescriber then send them to
to threehour preparation. Not everyone
in three-hour preparation. Well, in
fact, we should be talking about whether
18 year old children should be allowed
to participate. 18 year old is still a
very young age. The brain is not forming
until 2 to three years old. That where
we're looking at high risk of adverse
reactions, not someone using Joel P1 or
not. And I I think the age is a big
concern to me personally. I I still this
day don't feel comfortable with the
18year-old cut off for for the
adolescence. But u that's a separate
conversation.
>> Yeah. And I do appreciate it. I guess I
was more thinking the GLP1's just I had
heard um some stories from Colorado
where it was very significantly delaying
reaction and I would like to avoid that
if we could but
um all right so we have patients may be
referred by any clinician. Did we want
to reduce the preparation sessions?
Yeah, I think there were two um pieces
of feedback on preparation and I I just
wanted to to echo um what someone uh
mentioned earlier on around I think it
was Eileen around um pain and the pain
protocols. So it maybe makes sense for
us to require a higher threshold of
preparation but in certain instances
pain is the example not the you know um
every example but one one example where
it maybe does not make sense for us to
require preparation for future uh for
future treatment. Um but I I don't have
a strong feeling other than the um
question about billing like whether we
can do two hours or two sessions that
are three hours um
yeah I don't I don't feel super strongly
about those um pieces but I think others
may
>> two hours adding up to three it's not
two threehour sessions
>> right and I think my feedback was just
for folks who are working within a
automatically integrated system and they
are billing, we want them to be able to
work within their billing codes. And I
think from Ann's comment, that might be
limited at 60 minutes and then 30. So we
want we just want the math to add up. So
if they're um if they're if they're
threehour sessions, that's really
actually three interactions,
but someone who understands and does
billing as a part of their practice
should jump in and make sure I got that
right.
>> Yeah. So would y'all be um good with
like two total hours of like prior to
administration at least?
No less than two hours prior to
administration initially and then um
may be reduced upon
it's called um
and then Larry
>> yeah I I I just want to bring back
something I said earlier Um, I think
there needs to be some language to
indicate that the amount of preparation
may need to be increased based on
specific conditions and we may need to
figure out how to how to write that in.
I I really I deeply do not think um as
someone who takes care of people with
PTSD and as a psychedelic therapist that
like you know two hours would be
adequate preparation for people that are
in um have complex PTSD. And I just want
to make sure that we that we have
language in there for safety for the
conditions. I just want to remind you
this our program is very different than
Oregon or Colorado. We're actually
dealing here with you know two very
challenging conditions treatment
resistant depression and complex PTSD.
And I just want to encourage the idea
that that there may need to be uh um
more specifications for therapy not just
for giving psilocybin.
So, were we wanting to stay with three
or did we want to do the two? Because
now I've heard both sides.
Well, I wonder um I think what we're
hearing, you know, if there's a variety
of opinions on this is maybe we don't
need to arrive at a decision today about
what the what the requirement is. I I
want to say too uh you know maybe the
role of this committee is to make the
baseline recommendations but then
follow-up work. I mean in we've been
talk like the theme of today is like
right how do we work differently within
a medically integrated model and maybe
one of the opportunities that's before
us
as a medically integrated model like
normally the care protocols are de in um
in an intervention are developed by uh
by the licensing boards of those who are
participating. And so that might be a
way for us to partner with providers and
um develop relationships with licensing
boards um and get into more of the
specificity that I'm hearing um you know
for for specific acuitities is going to
be necessary but it's perhaps that's
just beyond the need of um of the the
work of this subcommittee.
Thank you. And don't worry about it. I
mean, we're I appreciate all input. So,
even if it's out of the scope, I'll let
you know. But I think that that could be
within. My concern is that I think it's
easier to make a baseline and then say
for specific conditions that they're
more strict than to make something
really strict and then say that um
conditions have exemptions. I don't I
know it's how my brain prefers to work,
but I am definitely open to um input on
that. And then I can see a hand up, but
I can't read the name. Johnny, do you
got me on that?
>> Yeah, it looks like Eileen. Um and I
think your mic is enabled.
>> Yeah, thank you. Um, I think that, yeah,
a one-sizefits-all approach to the
amount of preparation time doesn't make
sense because as somebody else said,
somebody could need more preparation
time, more time to set intention to
really consider what they're about to
do, especially if they're facing some
very difficult past trauma. Um but other
people might only need an hour of
preparation if they are um facing less
of that that trauma burden and more of
like they're already set in their
intentions and they've they've already
done a lot of the work or if they've had
past preparation sessions or they're
already very familiar with the process
and they're not new to the substance and
the treatment.
Thank you. And Chris,
>> I was just going to say I agree with
you, Ian, that maybe setting a low
baseline like two hours like you have is
a good idea and then um
maybe making the recommendation for more
based on
people with complex PTSD or other
qualifying conditions that might be more
difficult.
All right. So, a minimum of two hour.
So, here's what I have set for the
language cuz I've been updating it while
we were talking. Um, participants shall
initially complete at least two
preparation sessions totaling no less
than 2 hours prior to administration.
Initially, this limit may be reduced if
repeated dosing with each session
lasting at least one hour and occurring
no less than 24 hours and no more than
60 days before administration.
Preparation shall be conducted by the
facilitator by the facilitator present
during administration whenever feasible
may occur via telealth when clinically
appropriate and shall be documented in
the participant record.
Cool. All right. Um,
Chris,
>> I'm just curious. Should we require one
of those hours to be in in person? I
know that might create some um
some issues with equity and
availability, but I also think it's
important to meet people in person if
you're going to be sitting with them.
Yeah. I I'd like to hear if anybody else
has thoughts on that.
>> Um looks like Lisa has her hand up next.
We'll go to Lisa.
>> Thank you. Yes, I have a question around
um the the sentence preparation should
be done by the same person as
facilitation when feasible. I think um
it's almost a mandatory if you working
with a client to prepare them for
psychedelic session a and then all of a
sudden a new facilitator shows up in a
session that can create a layer of
stress and distrust for the client. So
um it almost should be a requirement
that preparation should be done by the
same facilitator
at least this at least one of the
preparations.
>> Thank you. and Denelli.
>> Um, yeah, on Chris's question about in
person, I think I agree that it might be
an equity issue and I agree it would be
great to codify our preference that it
be in person. And so maybe the um the
solution is we could say one of those
preparation sessions is in person where
practical feasible. So it allows for
folks who are in rural areas or
otherwise can't still to be able to
participate but um still enumerates our
preference.
Perfect. I have updated it. And James,
>> great topic with the in person. You
know, I I really think we need to look
at that too and say as as a facilitator,
you always want to be in person. You
always want that face to face. Um, we
live in New Mexico with 2 million
people, you know, in a very rural state.
We're the fifth largest. A lot of people
don't have ability to get there or
facilitator to get there. So, you think
about that both ways, right? I think if
it's not just the patient in this one,
how does the facilitator get to hobbs if
there's nobody there? How does the
facilitator get to, you know, Clovis or
somewhere else where these services are
so rural
um that you can't get there in person or
the cost is so extraordinary exum cost
that you can't get there in
affordability, you know, to that patient
cost. We got to keep this to a minimal
cost basis or is, you know, so I just
thought about that. That's all. I do
like the in person. I do with at least
maybe a minimum of one. I am a big fan
of in person, but I just want everybody
to think about that with the access and
cost with this one. Thank you.
>> Thank you. And I think actually Denali
got that pretty well by saying where
feasible 1 hour preparation shall be in
person because there are going to be
situations where it's not feasible. I
mean, as much as I would prefer for this
to be the situation, I do recognize that
again, we're in the fifth largest
geographical state. So, um, yeah, I
would I concur with that. Uh, any other
comments?
I will just go ahead and read. Um,
Elijah Trujillo said, "Hi, my name is
Elijah. As an average consumer, just
adds a layer of further screening to go
through to get an allotted micro dose
supply. However, having a data tracking
system that acts as a journal to report
where it is being experienced. I do
agree to experience consumers should go
through 1 to 1 and 1/2 hour screening
that determine if further screening is
needed when concerns arise like major
health conditions. Thank you. All right.
So if that is good on the
minimum preparation sessions, um is
everyone good with the informed consent
section?
Cool.
Uh so preparation shall include
orientation of the treatment process
including role and scope of facilitator
um
during and after administration and
shall include development of an
integration plan. Participants shall
discuss goals, intentions and
expectations and preparation shall
address set and setting factors
including psychological readiness,
environmental conditions, privacy,
accommodations and safety. Oh, Chris had
his hand up. I probably should have
looked
>> for the uh for the informed consent
portion. Um, do we need to make
individual recommendations as to what
should be included in that section or
are we going to leave it up to
Department of Health to kind of create
that on their own and then,
you know, try to change it from the back
end. I I feel like we could spend some
time really kind of hammering down what
should be included in that document.
Okay.
So, did you want to strike the entire
informed consent section or
>> No, I'm just
I'm just curious if and if I'm the only
one here, it's fine. we can leave it up
to department of health but um I think
you know that's a important part of this
process and
you know I I'm familiar with Colorado's
model and I like the way that they did
their informed consent document because
I I really think it gets to the bottom
of some of the the places where this
medicine has been abused over time and
and things like that and I just wonder
if we shouldn't be more thorough as to
what kind of sections they should
include. Um, but again, if I'm the only
one here, then
I'll let let it move on without that.
>> Pick uh, Denali.
>> Yeah, I don't actually know what my
perspective is. Maybe I'll find it
through the way, but I I just think I my
understanding of this document, right,
we're not writing the regulations or
even recommending them. I mean, I think
at the end of the day, whatever lives in
rules and rags that's proposed on this
is is probably going to be a lot more
bare bones. And then, right, it I I
don't actually know how the informed
consent document that you're
referencing, Chris, was developed, if it
was through the agency or if it was
through the professional association. I
mean informed consent is a really
important part of this process and I I
just don't know if we need um right
other than in this guiding document if
right this is how it will live in um in
rules and regulations it's also
something that individual linen with um
legal counsel are going to want to um
yeah have some recommendation about what
it is but I want to hear what Chris has
to say.
>> I think it's also just a a challenging
subject because you're trying to like
how do you get informed consent from
somebody who's never had a psychedelic
experience before to to have this
without setting expectation and um other
things. It's just
it's just a
very difficult subject. I think that
without
um kind of consulting the people that
have been doing this work for a long
time, I think the Department of Health
can really
miss on how that is put into play.
So
I guess
so your thing is that you want um us to
like build
a specific informed consent document
>> or at least
recommend
um you know all the the parts that we
think should be required in it.
>> So what is missing so far?
>> It would we don't have much. We have one
paragraph on informed consent here.
>> Yeah. So
>> well I'm not
let me uh let me try to pull up Colorado
and I can look at a few things that I
think we might want to include.
>> If there's also like a publicly
accessible link, you could also drop
that in the chat.
Okay. And I see Sky looks like uh
possibly dropped that in the chat.
Um, while we're reading that too, I see
Rob's got his hand up. Um, uh, Dr.
Tuckner, if you want to, uh, speak to
any of that.
>> Yeah, I just have to say there is so
much experience.
>> Oh, I think your boom is up still.
>> Still. Damn it. Um, excuse my language.
Um, there is
There is a lot of experience out there
and I I think Chris is right. We would
love a lot of input, maybe not
prescriptive
input, but there's so much experience
out there of writing consent forms from
different states. We are quite open to
reading it all as we begin to think
about crafting a a reasonable policy for
our state. Thank you.
All right. And I see Lisa's got her hand
up as well. Um Lisa, if you want to
unmute.
Thank you. Uh one of the things that I
see that's missing from the informed
consent is a use of touch and um option
to refuse use of touch during the
session uh among many other things. But
that's just something that stood out for
me.
Uh it's not in the informed consent but
it is in the safety and support plan. Um
it can include emergency procedures,
facility safety protocols. Um
it will also establish clear boundaries
including participant preferences
regarding physical touch, consent
processes and disclosure of any
additional persons or recording during
the session.
I I think touch should be also in the
informed consent.
>> Okay.
>> Because you you consent to touch.
And just one last comment. I think we
should also include that facilitator can
opt out from offering touch as well just
as as the client.
>> All right. And while
>> Oh, sorry. You can go.
I was just gonna see uh since it was
looked like you're still updating stuff
if we were going to go to Greg. Um so I
will unmute. All right, Gregory, you can
uh unmute yourself. Oh, and just
introduce yourself real quick.
>> Yeah, I got in late. My name is Gregory
Evans, independent researcher, no
affiliations, Santa Fe.
um it might be worthwhile to break out
what we are consenting to into
categories and that way people are not
bucket consenting to whatever we have we
can say this is informed consent for
consumption this is informed consent for
um session practices and so on that way
we can disambiguate the um what I would
consider a very broad
brush
Right. And I do want to remind everyone
that we do not have to get into the
specifics of everything. We are our job
is to provide recommendations to the
department so that they can create the
actual documents. It is not our
job to like actually like create an like
informed consent form. We just have to
say what is on the form. Um and then
they would take it from there.
Uh James
Ian on this just a last thing on the
consent thing that we haven't talked
about is I think we need a facilitator
consent form and we also need that
patient consent. Usually we use two. So
I think there needs to be a separation
between again the facilitator having
their own consent form to understand
what they're going to be doing and as
well as definitely the patient consent
form but we haven't talked about the
facilitator side. I think we need
something there as well. Thank you.
>> All right. And Denali,
>> I'm wondering if it might be helpful.
That was actually really helpful for me
to hear you say, Ian, um, that we're our
job is to make recommendations to do. I
wonder since our job is not to actually
figure out informed consent, maybe this
section is more appropriate as a
recommendation
that so we just say the subcommittee
recommends that the department adopt a
informed consent policy that considers
XYZ. You know, we heard um uh physical
touch. I heard the recommendation that
you know maybe consent not be bucket but
that it be enumerated.
Um
maybe I don't know if there was
consensus on this but that there be a do
specific form that individual
um licensed facilities can adopt um
something like that.
Okay. So I've added that. So I
definitely
um love what you said. I just have to
get this out because otherwise I will
forget it. So participant and fac and
facilitator informed consent cons
consent shall be obtained through direct
discussion and shall not be satisfied
solely by written acknowledgement. Um
and then
uh the D
form consent form
notifying
Okay. So, participant and facilitator
informed consent shall be obtained
through direct discussion and shall not
be satisfied solely by written
acknowledgement. The DOH shall create an
informed consent form notifying the
patient of what psilocybin is, overview
of psilocybin use, description of
psilocybin treatment, possible
side/adverse effects associated with
treatment, as well as possible benefits
associated with psilocybin use.
Preparation shall also establish clear
boundaries including participant/f
facilitator preferences regarding
physical touch, consent processes, and
disclosure of any additional persons or
recording during the session. The
discussion
The discussion shall include risks,
benefits, uncertainties, and
psychological and physical effects such
as altered states of consciousness,
potential impairment of decision-making,
and disclosure that facil that
psilocybin has not been approved by the
FDA. Written disclosure shall include
facilitator identity, permanent number
qualifications, any ceremonial
components, and the rights of the both
participant and facilitator to terminate
services.
questions, comments, concerns.
All right. So, preparation shall include
orientation to the treatment process,
including the role and scope of
facilitator and expectations before,
during, and after administration, and
shall include development of an
integration plan. Participants shall
discuss goals, intentions, and
expectations. And preparation shall
address set and setting factors
including psychological readiness,
environmental conditions, privacy,
accommodations, and safety.
Good.
Any hands, questions, comments,
concerns?
Cool. For group administration, at least
one individual preparation session shall
be required. At least one hour of group
preparation shall occur in the group
setting. This may be counted as part of
the total preparation hours.
Participants shall be informed of group
size, facilitator to participant ratio,
interaction expectations,
confidentiality, and physical contact
considerations,
questions, comments, concerns.
And then all preparation activities
shall be documented in the participant
record including session details.
>> Oh, Larry.
>> Yeah. Hi. I I apologize. I I had to drop
off for a little bit. Um I just want to
make a pitch that I really don't think
one hour in a group session is adequate
for people to establish connection and
safety with each other. Um I would say
the group visit needs to be you know two
two hours. I mean, you're talking about
I mean, a common site might be having
six people at a visit. I mean, they're
not going to get to know each other at
all in a 1 hour time frame.
>> Thank you. Does anyone agree with Larry
Deni?
Yeah, just raising my hand in agreement.
Um, I think that group settings and
safety are unique and maybe need um a
little bit more attention around safety
>> James
>> and Ian with the language on the group
sessions are we assuming that it's less
than
no less than 24 hours and no more than
60 days. Is that what we're kind of
still saying there? Is that still
indicated?
>> Yes.
and Chris.
>> Um, could we potentially have, you know,
one of those hours be
within 24 hours of the session? I I'm
trying to just figure out how we can
balance
um
access and equity with this safety. And
you know, if if we have
I think that would put it up to at least
three hours for um group preparation now
because correct me if I'm wrong. Do they
they have to have at least one
individual session if they're going to
be in groups as well?
because I think that's an important
part, right?
>> Theoretically
the hours are counted as part of the
preparation hours. So we could either
not count it as part or we have to
increase the amount of default
preparation time in order to create
there to be an over one hour. But um
currently because originally it was
written as at least 1 hour that way it
still worked with the um preparation
being at least two sessions but with it
being 2 hours um it could count as at
least one of them um assuming it's one
big 2hour session.
Um,
yeah, if it's one big 2-hour session, it
would count as one, but if they split it
into two 1-hour sessions, then that
would count as two under my current
understanding. Uh, Larry,
>> I think he just might have had his hand
up from leftover.
>> Correct. Sorry about that.
>> No worries, Eileen.
Um, I believe that the point of allowing
group sessions was to reduce costs and
increasing preparation increases cost
which reduces accessibility for so many
people. I mean, as we've seen in Oregon,
only wealthy people are able to access
these services anyway. And how it's
being set up is that's going to be
pretty much the case here as well. So, I
would think that we would want to be
reducing costs as much as possible. And
I recognize that there's a safety issue,
but hopefully the the facilitators will
be able to choose groups that they think
would work together.
>> Thank you.
>> Okay. And Larry, did you have a comment
after that?
>> Yeah. I I I I just want to maybe remind
all of us that like some of what we're
talking about here which of things like
group group sessions for PTSD. There is
very little experience um you know with
doing any kind of a model with this
little preparation. I mean the this has
happened in certain retreat settings
where we're doing that. We're actually
starting a study at UNO which has far
more um preparation in it and it it it
doesn't have to do with the psilocybin
so much as some of the some of the
indications. I think maybe we could
phrase something in there because I I I
really do appreciate the you know the um
the access issues and you know for
instance if this was going to be um six
people that were meeting and they're all
have nicotine dependence and it's for
nicotine dependence. I don't feel like
that you know that they need that. So
perhaps there could be something written
in here that, you know, discusses the
idea of having more required preparation
for certain indications. I'm not sure
how to work that through because it
deals with different committees, but I'm
I'm just very concerned about the the
complex PTSD and um and I I know that we
can say we expect that the facilitators
will make wise decisions, but part of
our safety thing is to mandate some some
minimums for those situations.
Yeah. And I do want to note that we are
going to go over like the specific um
like conditions, the specific qualifying
conditions. We're going to still give
specific which dosage tier they fall
into um by default and then which um
like extra steps have to be taken for
that specific condition cuz the clinical
practice is going to differentiate
depending on what you are treating. Um,
so I definitely do expect that in the
future we will. What I can go ahead and
add for the time being is um
like
um if necessary
additional preparation may be required.
All righty. So, since we did get through
preparation today,
just am going to post it in the chat so
that we can all review
what we are
>> and I have
>> Oh, hey Chris.
>> I have one recommendation. Maybe could
we um I feel like if people are forced
to do their entire preparation in groups
that doesn't give them any individual
time to
uh express concerns that they maybe
wouldn't bring up in the group. Could we
make the recommendation that they have
an opportunity for a
one-on-one integration or preparation
session uh of some length to express
those concerns?
So I changed the group administration to
be for group administration at least one
individual preparation session shall be
required. At least 2 hours of group
preparation shall occur in the group
setting. This may be counted as part of
as part of the total preparation hours
so long as one one individual hour of
prep is recorded. Would that be good for
you? because I do agree that there
should be at least one individual. I
just wanted to make sure that that
language was okay with that ground.
>> So, does it does that bump it up to
three at that point in time or does that
say if you were doing a group, you would
have a 2hour group facilitation and then
you would have a oneh hour individual.
Could we make that one hour potentially
optional so that you know it could be
the like they have to provide it if
if people want it but if you know if
people are feeling prepared with the
group sessions then it it's
Oh,
so for group administration, at least
one individual preparation session is
recommended. However, a patient may
decline if they opt out. At least 2
hours of group preparation shall occur
in a group setting. This may be counted
as part of the total preparation hours.
Uh actually hold on going to Yeah,
that's fine. Um participants shall be
informed of group size, facilitator to
participant ratio, interaction
expectations, confidentiality, and
physical contact considerations. Uh
James,
>> one thing here, Ian, that we haven't
said with the group is uh that we come
into is group agreements, group
confidentiality.
Um you know, because now you're not just
individually with that facilitator,
facilitator, and those other people who
with that confidentiality can come in.
So we definitely let them know about
confidentiality and they do sign
something uh on that saying hey these
other members in here you have to be
conf you know that's all
>> and
Chris
>> so um I can't remember if we put
anything in here that um reduces
requirements for follow on
um sessions in both group and individual
sessions. Is that is this the place that
we'd want to add something in?
>> Uh I did at the very top. It just hasn't
been on the screen for a little bit. It
says um
>> so they initially must do two hours
prior to administration, but this limit
may be reduced if repeating dosing.
>> Okay. And so that would apply to the
group as well then.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. Thanks you and sorry.
>> Yeah, no worries.
>> And then I see Sky hand up. Um Sky or uh
mic is enabled. You can unmute when
ready. Oh, and just I I don't know if I
don't remember if you introduce yourself
in the chat, but if not, you can
introduce yourself as well.
And the uh mic unmute button is up at
the should be up at the top right hand
part of teams.
>> Oh, okay. You can hear me fine.
>> Uhhuh. Thanks.
>> Oh, beautiful. I'm Sky Rivers. I'm with
the Santa Fe reporter. I've been
following these meetings and I first I
want to commend everybody for
participating, especially all those
putting these committees together. They
have been quite educational. I think
you're doing a fabulous job. That being
said, I think I missed something. um
earlier and so please correct me if I'm
wrong on the group sessions are they
qualifying to be in the group some
people will have more severe trauma than
others and I am wondering does anybody
qualify for a group or those everybody
qualify whoever qualifies qualifies to
be in the program but maybe not
everybody qualifies to be in a group
session where there could be uh
situations I used to be involved
involved with groups and such in the Bay
Area and you have to be really careful
when you put a bunch of people together
who are dealing with um challenging
issues. So I'm did I miss that part of
it in this talk?
So uh we had not come to a specific
conclusion but some of the things that I
had heard um we might want to do is to
basically set um have the facilitators
select their groups so that if they are
um and maybe their patient participation
but um having that facilitator since
they are going to be the ones
responsible kind of make their who they
think will work together best and that
kind of
which would mean then that they have
been pre-qualified or they know who
these people are. Correct.
>> Yeah, they've already been referred by a
clinician. And then once the they have
the referral, that's when the
facilitating office or whatever you want
to call it takes over.
>> Um and then at that point, um they could
say, okay, well, you know, maybe there
it's a group of friends who have, like
Larry said, who have nicotine addiction.
They want to do it together. I'm sure
the facilitator would be fine with that,
but once it gets into the more I have
three patients with um complex PTSD,
that that's where it becomes a little
bit riskier. So, since it is in the
facilitator's hands, I would imagine it
in um
them being the ones to decide the
groups.
>> Thank you. Appreciate it.
All
right, I've thrown the preparation um
session in the chat
um so that it can be reviewed and we can
um
>> All right, Ian before you can continue
there is one question in the chat uh by
Elijah Is there consideration guidelines
for anonymized uh data sharing to
support research and policy refinement?
>> Yes, via the um research and continuous
improvement committee are working on um
anonymized data sharing to ensure that
the program is is as optimal as it can
be.
>> I can I can post the next uh research
committee in the chat for you as well.
>> Perfect. Thank you.
All righty.
So, this took up a little bit more time
than I was expecting. So, we will go
ahead and have our vote on preparation.
Before we vote, is there any other
changes that we think need to be made,
comments, questions, concerns?
Uh, Chris
Yeah, we can vote on specifically the
prescriber issue an if you would like.
Um, but it has already been changed on
this issue to participant may be
referred by any clinician. Um, because
that did seem like it was the consensus.
But if you want a specific vote, we
absolutely can.
>> I was just going to ask if we could
maybe vote on it at the beginning of the
next meeting. So, uh, if other people
had comments or, um, things that we
could, uh, we could write in, uh, and
take a look at the the minutes,
but if you feel like it's ready for a
vote, this is your show.
Um,
so what I typically do in my committees,
and I'm just going to share in is what
we'll do is we'll adopt the preparation.
We'll adopt the administration, we'll
adopt the integration, and then we'll
adopt a conjoined version. Um,
so once we even have all of these three,
we can do the conjoined and that's where
we would add in um some public comment
and give just another chance for a group
of people to look it over and say, "Hey,
is this good? Hey, is this um not good?"
Um, but I definitely would be okay with
waiting until the next meeting if you
guys would prefer um that.
And then Ann, with that um change, did
you still want to vote on the prescriber
issue?
I just don't want to leave any thoughts
unattended to
Yes.
Um,
>> yeah. Sorry, just a sec. Um,
oh, there you are. Okay. All right. You
are unmuted.
>> Great. No, I think that um that looks
fine. I just, you know, when you were
typing earlier, I wasn't sure if you had
adopted what James had said um or if it
was just the referred by any clinician.
I do think that it would be important to
specify that the clinician needs to have
diagnosis as um part of the scope of
practice that they have just so that
like you know massage therapists aren't
you know diagnosing people with
treatment resistant depression or thing.
All right.
So, participant may be referred by any
clinician with
All right. So, participant may be
referred by any clinician acting within
their scope of practice with the ability
to diagnose.
All right.
Any
other changes?
>> Looks like Denali's got her hand up. Uh,
Denali can unmute.
>> Hi. Um, I raised my hand when we were
talking about voting. Um, and I guess I
was curious, maybe this is a question
for the department. It would be helpful
to know in this question of when we need
to vote
if the like when are the associated
rules on um on this needed by and what
is that timeline? Um and then I was
going to ask this was kind of related to
what Chris mentioned um just as a
procedural issue or request um would be
is it possible for the documents to be
shared a little bit earlier out? They
tend to come about 30 minutes before a
meeting, but I didn't have time to
review before. That would be helpful too
to being
>> Yeah. So, I'll I'll speak to that real
quick. Um, so yeah, I can
uh what I can try to do is just kind of
check daily. So, like what I did because
I sent it out twice. Once was like last
week. Um.
>> Oh, okay. Sorry.
>> When Ian gave it to me.
>> Um, yeah. now. So, I can I can just try
to check the um the sign up uh more
regularly just so I can send that out
because Yeah. What? So far, it's usually
like I'll send it out like a Usually Ian
will have it ready like a week before
and I'll send it out.
>> Okay, great. No, then this is a user
error. This was my problem.
>> No, no worries.
>> Thank you for having it.
>> Sure. Yeah, but I I will I'll I'll try
to be I'll I'll try to check it more
often just so I can get people in in
between.
>> Yeah. Yeah. And then does anybody from
DOH know like are the associated rules
for this when is the department hoping
to have draft rules?
>> Hi Dali this is so uh uh we are as as
you know the rules for uh propagation
will be are are open to the public and I
just want to make that announcement. So,
uh you can find those the link to the
website for those uh for public comment
and we will have a public hearing April
24th uh which will be hybrid uh and we
uh so with that uh we have not discussed
in great uh um detail with Ian, but we
can talk more about that Ian um and and
time went when we're talking about uh uh
putting together these rules, you know.
>> Yeah. Um, so yeah, as soon as we
typically get them over from the board
side to the department, they pretty are
pretty quick on it. Um, but we are
currently they are currently um working
on the rule making process.
All right.
>> Yeah, I if if I may, this is Robert
Sharker, Denali, I think your question
is, do you have time to review these and
read these? Yes, you do. If uh Ian, if
you choose to put this off to the next
meeting, that certainly works within our
timeline.
>> Okay. Yeah. Then we'll just go ahead and
postpone this. I will um get the version
sent out with the edits that we made
after this meeting and then um we will
be good to reconvene then. Sound good?
What I can
>> what I can also do with this um uh yeah
this particular version instead of uh
sending it just to people who sign up
for the next meeting I can send it to
everybody who uh attended this meeting
as well um just so that everybody gets
it. And again I also want to make the
announcement uh that these do get posted
onto the uh the medical psilocybin
website and you can take a look at
those. That does take several days cuz
that has to get approval from our our
marketing and communications department.
So, uh that's a that's a little bit
longer process, but uh Johnny will send
those out for those who are keep present
and who have signed up, but also like
for those who are uh have not already
registered, you can pass the word to
them that they can take a look at those
in several days when they are posted.
>> Perfect. All righty. Does anyone have
any preference on the next time we meet?
How does April 13th sound to everyone?
see how that looks on our end.
All righty. Then with no objection, we
will be meeting on April 13th at 9:00
a.m. I thank you all for showing up.
Thank you for spending time with us
today. I appreciate all your input and
even if we may not agree on everything,
I still do appreciate you taking the
time and discussing it with us. I am
proud of the work that we do. And thank
you guys again.
And if you want to submit public
comments, please do so by the uh
tomorrow at 5:00 p.m.
Thank you everyone.